instinct that which comes from within
without a call that which calls from
within outwards that which is inherent
to a being sets of behavior sets of
perceptions ways of understanding
flexible and inflexible imprints
instincts that drive forwards that push
forwards the bubble force like magma as
a volcano have an instinct instinct as a
volcano have an instinct such as volcano
does it have properties an interesting
boundary condition might be plants
plants have tendencies to grow towards
light to grow away from gravity roots
grow towards gravity are there they are
those instincts are they is its it's
very difficult to pin down exactly where
an instinct is the notion of instinct
pushing outwards into the world is quite
interesting and so it's something to do
with the way with which we interface
with the world and instincts has a
connotation of being embedded somehow
right that you'll sort of stuck with
your instincts can you instinct be
modified can you learn instincts or our
instincts that you sort of stuck with
them you can manage them but but but you
have what you have
instincts like magnetic poles being
drawn out of us by great forces the
plant reaches towards the light is
pulled down into gravity the sources of
our instincts maybe do not lie within
but actually lie without that a great
call is happening from the outside world
beckoning us to form some kind of dance
to perform some kind of dance to
interact with the world in a specific
way great distant forces being
actualized here now in the present
moment that's very interesting instinct
not as standalone things but as part of
a system a way of speaking to a form of
language communication sets with
external reality so that's that's very
interesting that the coupling of so an
instinct emerges as a consequence of a
need for that instinct to emerge being
presented in the environment and so
that's very interesting
so what we have in us then are like the
seeds of instinct waiting to be
activated by being alive and being
active in an environment something like
that instinct to breathe only possible
when there is a continual source of life
to nourish first the fetus
and then the newborn the oxygen for the
breath to happen one half within one
heart without this poor desire to pull
in or his outside transmute it within
and then to give back to the environment
does the universe have an instinct
towards greater complexity which a
deeper entropy to the lifelessness hmm
very interesting it seems like it might
be interesting to explore the boundaries
between instinct and tendency instinct
and intuition instinct and reflex
instinct and I don't know other forms of
autonomic type reactions to
circumstances in the environment where
are the boundaries between these things
is instinct maybe oh is instinct maybe
the participate or II knowing and then
stacks on top of that moving up when you
get to the propositional that's
intuition is it maybe something like
that is that is there some way of
putting it into Vevey keys framework
instinct as deep biological wisdom
sourced from the beginning of time when
the first life was born how to stay
alive how to stay alive - their lives
the question of the instincts figuring
out by any means how to keep this
life-form lifing to keep this life-form
forming
in you the metabolism to continue the
process life being born the first
instinct arising life being born may be
a blank no knowledge just physical pause
and drifts and sways and remembering
which sways and pulls and pushes worked
the best and saving them for future
generations so instincts are linked to
our deep ancestry if they've evolved
over large amounts of time they are also
linked to our ancestry it also if you if
if one strips down instinct to being an
instinct for survival that there is
actually only one instinct that that and
that is to survive and that all of the
other things which have become instincts
are modest on modifications hacks of
that basic instinct for survival which
then manifests as an instinctive grouse
Awards sunlight for example because
appliance chances of survival are better
if it is able to do that but I wonder if
is there's a single root two instinct on
the origin of life from multiple origins
of life multiple branches on the life
tree or what point is there
a phase shift when the new cortex comes
online when the CCO neocortex comes
online what kind of phase shifts happen
instincts what happens when we finally
access the tino global scale and rewrite
our instincts this thing's rewriting
instinct that what's necessary to
present prevent us from going extinct
rewriting the code of life rewriting our
destinies is that even possible to
rewrite instincts bring them into
awareness and manage them
yes but rewrite code which is in some
cases hundreds of millions or billions
of years old I mean that's really slow
code and yeah rewriting that seems like
an impossible task there's maybe some
value in the idea of a switch of focus
to not quite such slow code when
thinking about instinct and so somehow
detaching the survival thing from all of
the other things that it has become and
allowing those to be rewritten